You know, one of the intense pleasures of travel
هل تعرفون أن أحد المتع الكبيرة للسفر
and one of the delights of ethnographic research
وأحد مباهج أبحاث الإثنوجرافيا
is the opportunity to live amongst those
في فرصة العيش بين أولئك
who have not forgotten the old ways,
الذين لم ينسوا الأساليب القديمة
who still feel their past in the wind,
الذين لا زالوا يشعرون بماضيهم في الرياح
touch it in stones polished by rain,
ويلمسونه في الأحجار التي صقلتها الأمطار
taste it in the bitter leaves of plants.
ويتذوقونه في أوراق النباتات المرة
Just to know that Jaguar shamans still journey beyond the Milky Way,
إن معرفة أن الشامان الجاكوار لا زالوا يسافرون بالإعتماد على مجرة درب التبانة
or the myths of the Inuit elders still resonate with meaning,
وأن أساطير عواجيز قبائل الإنويت لا تزال معانيها تلاقي صدى
or that in the Himalaya,
وكذلك الأساطير الموجودة في الهيمالايا
the Buddhists still pursue the breath of the Dharma,
وأن البوذيون لا يزالون يبحثون عن روح دارما،
is to really remember the central revelation of anthropology,
هي في الحقيقة تجلي للفكرة الأساسية للأنثربولوجيا
and that is the idea that the world in which we live
وهي فكرة أن العالم الذي نعيش فيه
does not exist in some absolute sense,
لا يوجد بشكل مطلق
but is just one model of reality,
لكنه نموذج واحد فقط للحقيقة.
the consequence of one particular set of adaptive choices
إنه نتيجة مجموعة معينة من اختيارات التكيف
that our lineage made, albeit successfully, many generations ago.
التي قام بها الجنس البشري بنجاح منذ عدة أجيال.
And of course, we all share the same adaptive imperatives.
إننا بالطبع نشترك في مبادئ التكيف
We're all born. We all bring our children into the world.
فنحن جميعاً ولدنا وننجب أطفالاً ليعيشوا في العالم
We go through initiation rites.
كما أننا جميعا نمر بتجارب الشعائر الاستهلالية
We have to deal with the inexorable separation of death,
وعلينا جميعاً أيضاً أن نتحمل فراق الموت القاسي.
so it shouldn't surprise us that we all sing, we all dance,
لذلك فإنها ليست مفاجأة لنا أن نكون جميعاً نمارس الغناء والرقس
we all have art.
وأننا جميعاً لدينا الفن.
But what's interesting is the unique cadence of the song,
لكن المثير في الأمر هو التناغم المميز للأغنية
the rhythm of the dance in every culture.
والإيقاع الفريد للرقص في كل ثقافة،
And whether it is the Penan in the forests of Borneo,
وسواء إذا كانت قبائل البينان في غابات بورنيو
or the Voodoo acolytes in Haiti,
أو مساعدي الكهنة الفودو في هاييتي
or the warriors in the Kaisut desert of Northern Kenya,
أو المحاربين في صحراء الكايسوت بشمال كينيا
the Curandero in the mountains of the Andes,
والكورانديرو في جبال الإنديز
or a caravanserai in the middle of the Sahara --
أو كارافانسيراي في وسط الصحراء الكبرى
this is incidentally the fellow that I traveled into the desert with
وبالمناسبة هذا هو الرجل الذي سافرت معه إلى داخل الصحراء
a month ago --
منذ شهر مضى.
or indeed a yak herder in the slopes of Qomolangma,
أو حتى صاحب قطيع ثيران تبت في وديان قومولانجما
Everest, the goddess mother of the world.
في إفرست، الإلهة الأم للعالم.
All of these peoples teach us that there are other ways of being,
كل هؤلاء الناس يعلموننا أنه يوجد أساليب أخرى للعيش
other ways of thinking,
وأساليب أخرى للتفكير
other ways of orienting yourself in the Earth.
وأساليب أخرى لتحقيق التكيف في الأرض.
And this is an idea, if you think about it,
إنها الفكرة ، التي إذا فكرت فيها
can only fill you with hope.
ستمتلئ بالأمل.
Now, together the myriad cultures of the world
والآن، فإن العدد الذي لا يعد ولا يحصى من الثقافات في العالم
make up a web of spiritual life and cultural life
يصنع شبكة من الحياة الروحية والحياة الثقافية
that envelops the planet,
لتغلف كوكب الأرض
and is as important to the well-being of the planet
وتساهم في مهمة الحفاظ عليه
as indeed is the biological web of life that you know as a biosphere.
كما تفعل الشبكة الحيوية للحياة التي تعرفونها باسم المحيط الحيوي.
And you might think of this cultural web of life
ويمكننا معرفة هذه الشبكة الثقافية للحياة باسم
as being an ethnosphere,
المحيط العرقي.
and you might define the ethnosphere
وربما يمكنك تعريف المحيط العرقي
as being the sum total of all thoughts and dreams, myths,
بكونه المجموع الإجمالي لكل الأفكار والأحلام والأساطير
ideas, inspirations, intuitions brought into being
والإلهامات والحدس المغروس في الفرد
by the human imagination since the dawn of consciousness.
بواسطة الخيال البشري منذ فجر الإدراك
The ethnosphere is humanity's great legacy.
إن المحيط العرقي هو التراث العظيم للبشرية،
It's the symbol of all that we are
إنه رمز لكل ما نحن عليه
and all that we can be as an astonishingly inquisitive species.
وكل ما يمكن أن نكون عليه كمخلوقات فضولية بشكل يثير الدهشة
And just as the biosphere has been severely eroded,
ومثلما يتعرض المحيط الحيوي للتآكل الشديد،
so too is the ethnosphere
يتعرض المحيط العرقي أيضاً للتآكل
-- and, if anything, at a far greater rate.
-- وربما بمعدل أكبر جداً
No biologists, for example, would dare suggest
على سبيل المثال، لا يمكن لعلماء البيولوجي أن يزعموا
that 50 percent of all species or more have been or are
أن 50% أو أكثر من كافة المخلوقات كانوا
on the brink of extinction because it simply is not true,
أو هم بالفعل على حافة الانقراض لأن هذا بكل بساطة غير صحيح،
and yet that -- the most apocalyptic scenario
غير أن -- أكثر السيناريوهات تشاؤماً
in the realm of biological diversity --
في عالم التعددية الحيوية --
scarcely approaches what we know to be the most optimistic scenario
تكاد تقترب لما نعرف أن يكون أكثر السيناريوهات تفاؤلاً
in the realm of cultural diversity.
في عالم التعددية الثقافية
And the great indicator of that, of course, is language loss.
وأكبر دليل على ذلك بالطبع هو فقدان اللغة.
When each of you in this room were born,
عندما ولد كل الأشخاص الموجودين في هذه الغرفة
there were 6,000 languages spoken on the planet.
كان يوجد 6000 لغة يتم التحدث بها على كوكبنا
Now, a language is not just a body of vocabulary
والآن، ليست اللغة مجرد وعاء للمعاني
or a set of grammatical rules.
أو مجموعة من القواعد النحوية
A language is a flash of the human spirit.
فاللغة هي ضوء للروح البشرية
It's a vehicle through which the soul of each particular culture
هي جسر تأتي عليه روح كل ثقافة معينة
comes into the material world.
إلى العالم المادي
Every language is an old-growth forest of the mind,
تعتبر كل لغة هي ثمرة العقل الذي أنتجها،
a watershed, a thought, an ecosystem of spiritual possibilities.
كما أنها خط فاصل وفكر ونظام بيئي خاص بالإمكانيات الروحية.
And of those 6,000 languages, as we sit here today in Monterey,
ومن تلك الـ 6000 لغة، حيث نجلس هنا اليوم في مونتيري
fully half are no longer being whispered into the ears of children.
أصبح نصف هذه اللغات لا يهمس بها في آذان الصغار
They're no longer being taught to babies,
ولا يتم تعليمهم إلى الأطفال الرضع
which means, effectively, unless something changes,
وهذا يعني أنه ما لم يحدث تغيير
they're already dead.
فقد ماتوا بالفعل
What could be more lonely than to be enveloped in silence,
ما الذي يمكن أن يكون أكثر وحدة من إنغلاقك في صمت
to be the last of your people to speak your language,
أو أن تكون آخر من يتحدث بلغة معينة،
to have no way to pass on the wisdom of the ancestors
أو ألا يكون لديك أي وسيلة تنقل بها حكمة أجدادك
or anticipate the promise of the children?
أو تتوقع المستقبل الواعد الذي ينتظر الأطفال؟
And yet, that dreadful fate is indeed the plight of somebody
إلا أن هذا القدر المرعب هو حتماً مأزق شخص ما
somewhere on Earth roughly every two weeks,
في مكان ما في الأرض كل أسبوعين تقريباً
because every two weeks, some elder dies
لأن كل أسبوعين، يموت أحد المسنين
and carries with him into the grave the last syllables
ويأخذ معه إلى القبر أخر مقطع لفظي
of an ancient tongue.
من أحد اللغات القديمة.
And I know there's some of you who say, "Well, wouldn't it be better,
قد يقول أحدكم الآن، "حسناً، ألن يكون ذلك أفضل؟
wouldn't the world be a better place
ألن يكون العالم مكاناً أفضل
if we all just spoke one language?" And I say, "Great,
إذا تحدثنا كلنا لغة واحدة؟" وأنا أقول، "عظيم
let's make that language Yoruba. Let's make it Cantonese.
لنجعل تلك اللغة ياروبا. لنجعلها كانتونيز.
Let's make it Kogi."
لنجعلها كوجي."
And you'll suddenly discover what it would be like
وستكتشف فجأة ماهية الشعور
to be unable to speak your own language.
أن تكون غير قادر على التحدث بلغتك.
And so, what I'd like to do with you today
ولهذا، ما أود أن أقوم به معكم اليوم
is sort of take you on a journey through the ethnosphere,
هو نوع من أخذكم في رحلة خلال المحيط العرقي --
a brief journey through the ethnosphere,
رحلة موجزة خلال المحيط العرقي
to try to begin to give you a sense of what in fact is being lost.
في محاولة لمنحكم أحد المعاني التي فقدناها بالفعل.
Now, there are many of us who sort of forget
يوجد عدد كبير منا الآن نوعاً ما لا يستوعب
that when I say "different ways of being,"
أنه عندما أقول "أساليب مختلفة من الحياة"
I really do mean different ways of being.
فإنني أعني فعلاً أساليب مختلفة من الحياة
Take, for example, this child of a Barasana in the Northwest Amazon,
خذ على سبيل المثال، هذا الطفل من باراسانا في شمال غرب الأمازون
the people of the anaconda
شعب الأناكوندا
who believe that mythologically they came up the milk river
الذين يؤمنون بأنهم جاؤوا عبر نهر اللبن
from the east in the belly of sacred snakes.
من الشرق في بطن أفاعي مقدسة
Now, this is a people who cognitively
الآن، هؤلاء ناس لا يفرقون
do not distinguish the color blue from the color green
إدراكياً بين اللون الأزرق واللون الأخضر
because the canopy of the heavens
لأن غطاء الجنة
is equated to the canopy of the forest
مساو لغطاء الغابة
upon which the people depend.
والتي يعتمد عليها الناس.
They have a curious language and marriage rule
هذا الشعب لدية قاعدة غريبة في الزواج تتعلق باللغة
which is called "linguistic exogamy:"
والتي تسمى التباعد اللغوي:
you must marry someone who speaks a different language.
أي أنك يجب أن تتزوج من شخص يتحدث لغة مختلفة
And this is all rooted in the mythological past,
وهذا كله متأصل في الماضي الميثولوجي
yet the curious thing is in these long houses,
إلا أن الغريب فعلاً يوجد في تلك المنازل الممتدة الأجيال
where there are six or seven languages spoken
حيث يتم التحدث بست أو سبع لغات
because of intermarriage,
بسبب الزواج المختلط
you never hear anyone practicing a language.
لن تسمع بأحد يدرس لغة
They simply listen and then begin to speak.
فهم ببساطة ينصتون ثم يبدأون في التحدث
Or, one of the most fascinating tribes I ever lived with,
أو، واحدة من أبرز القبائل التي عشت معها
the Waorani of northeastern Ecuador,
الواوراني في شمال شرق الإكوادور
an astonishing people first contacted peacefully in 1958.
وهم أناس مدهشون تم الاتصال بهم لأول مرة عام 1958
In 1957, five missionaries attempted contact
في عام 1957، حاول خمسة مبشرين الاتصال بهم
and made a critical mistake.
وارتكبوا خطأ فادحاً
They dropped from the air
فقد أسقطوا من الجو
8 x 10 glossy photographs of themselves
صور لامعة لأنفسهم ثمانية بوصات في عشرة بوصات
in what we would say to be friendly gestures,
فيما يمكن أن نقول عليه خطوة ودية
forgetting that these people of the rainforest
ناسين أن هؤلاء الناس من الغابات المطيرة
had never seen anything two-dimensional in their lives.
لم يروا أي شيئ ثنائي الأبعاد في حياتهم
They picked up these photographs from the forest floor,
التقطوا هذه الصور من أرض الغابة
tried to look behind the face to find the form or the figure,
حاولوا النظر خلف الوجه للعثور على الشكل أو الجسم
found nothing, and concluded that these were calling cards
ولكن لم يجدوا شيئ، وتوصلوا إلى أن هذه بطاقات استدعاء
from the devil, so they speared the five missionaries to death.
من الشيطان، ولذا فقد قتلوا الخمسة مبشرين.
But the Waorani didn't just spear outsiders.
ولكن الواوروني لا يقتلون الأجانب فقط.
They speared each other.
فقد قتلوا بعضهم البعض.
54 percent of their mortality was due to them spearing each other.
54% من نسبة وفياتهم كانت نتيجة قتلهم لبعض.
We traced genealogies back eight generations,
ولقد رصدنا الأنساب لثمانية أجيال مضت
and we found two instances of natural death
ووجدنا حادثين لموت طبيعي
and when we pressured the people a little bit about it,
وحين ضغطنا على الناس قليلا حولها
they admitted that one of the fellows had gotten so old
اعترفوا أن أحد الزملاء أصبح مسناً
that he died getting old, so we speared him anyway. (Laughter)
وأنه سيموت بسبب السن، فقتلناه على كل حال.
But at the same time they had a perspicacious knowledge
ولكن هذه القبيلة تتمتع في الوقت ذاته بمعرفة ثاقبة
of the forest that was astonishing.
في أمور الغابة إلى درجة تثير الدهشة.
Their hunters could smell animal urine at 40 paces
ويمكن أن يشم صيادوهم رائحة بول حيوان على بعد 40 خطوة
and tell you what species left it behind.
ويخبرك بنوع الحيوان الذي تركها.
In the early '80s, I had a really astonishing assignment
في أوائل الثمانينيات، كان عندي مهمة مدهشة فعلاً
when I was asked by my professor at Harvard
وعندما سألني أستاذي في هارفارد
if I was interested in going down to Haiti,
إذا كنت مهتم بالذهاب إلى هاييتي
infiltrating the secret societies
للتوغل في المجتمعات السرية
which were the foundation of Duvalier's strength
والتي كانت قوة المؤسس دوفالييه
and Tonton Macoutes,
وتونتون ماكوتس
and securing the poison used to make zombies.
والحصول على السم المستخدم لصناعة "زومبيز".
In order to make sense out of sensation, of course,
ولكي أستوعب ذلك
I had to understand something about this remarkable faith
يجب أن أفهم شيئاً عن هذا الإيمان
of Vodoun. And Voodoo is not a black magic cult.
الخاص بالفودون، والفودو ليس جماعة سحر أسود.
On the contrary, it's a complex metaphysical worldview.
على العكس، فهو نظرة عالمية ميتافيزيقية معقدة
It's interesting.
هو أمر شيق
If I asked you to name the great religions of the world,
إذا طلبت منك أن تذكر أسماء الديانات العظمى في العالم
what would you say?
أيها ستقول؟
Christianity, Islam, Buddhism, Judaism, whatever.
المسيحية، الإسلام، البوذية، اليهودية، وأي شئ
There's always one continent left out,
يوجد دائما قارة واحدة متروكة
the assumption being that sub-Saharan Africa
على افتراض أن أفريقيا تحت الصحراء الكبرى
had no religious beliefs. Well, of course, they did
ليس لديها معتقدات دينية. حسناً، بالطبع لديهم
and Voodoo is simply the distillation
والفودود هو القطارة
of these very profound religious ideas
لهذه الأفكار الدينية المتعمقة جداً
that came over during the tragic Diaspora of the slavery era.
والتي جاءت خلال الشتات المأسوي لعصر العبودية.
But, what makes Voodoo so interesting
ولكن الذي يجعل الفودو شيقاً جداً هو
is that it's this living relationship
أنه علاقة حية
between the living and the dead.
بين الحي والميت
So, the living give birth to the spirits.
لذلك، يعطي الحي الحياة للأرواح.
The spirits can be invoked from beneath the Great Water,
ويمكن استحضار الأرواح من تحت المياه العظيمة
responding to the rhythm of the dance
استجابة إلى إيقاع الموسيقى
to momentarily displace the soul of the living,
لكي تحل محل روح الانسان الحي لحظياً
so that for that brief shining moment, the acolyte becomes the god.
وفي تلك اللحظة اللامعة القصيرة، يصبح الاكوليت هو الإله.
That's why the Voodooists like to say
ولذلك يحب أتباع الفودو أن يقولوا
that "You white people go to church and speak about God.
"أنتم أيها البيض تذهبون إلى الكنيسة وتتحدثون عن الرب.
We dance in the temple and become God."
بينما نحن نرقص في المعبد ونصبح آلهة."
And because you are possessed, you are taken by the spirit --
ولأنك تكون مسيطر عليك، والروح تتملكك
how can you be harmed?
كيف يمكن أن تتأذى؟
So you see these astonishing demonstrations:
لذا فأنت ترى هذه المشاهدات العجيبة:
Voodoo acolytes in a state of trance
أعوان الفودو في حالة فقدان وعي
handling burning embers with impunity,
وهم يمسكون بجمرات مشتعلة بدون أي ألم
a rather astonishing demonstration of the ability of the mind
وهو تجربة مذهلة لقدرة العقل
to affect the body that bears it
في التأثير على الجسد الذي يحمله
when catalyzed in the state of extreme excitation.
عند تحفيزها في حالة إثارة بالغة
Now, of all the peoples that I've ever been with,
الآن، من بين كل الناس الذين كنت معهم
the most extraordinary are the Kogi
فإن الأكثر غرابة كانت قبيلة الكوجي
of the Sierra Nevada de Santa Marta in northern Colombia.
من سييرا نيفادا دي سانتا مارتا في شمال كولومبيا.
Descendants of the ancient Tairona civilization
سلالة حضارة استبدادية قديمة
which once carpeted the Caribbean coastal plain of Colombia,
والتي كانت موجودة على ساحل الكاريبي لكولومبيا
in the wake of the conquest,
وفي أعقاب الغزو،
these people retreated into an isolated volcanic massif
تراجع هؤلاء الناس إلى قمم جبال بركانية معزولة
that soars above the Caribbean coastal plain.
والتي تشرف على السهل الساحلي الكاريبي.
In a bloodstained continent,
في قارة ملطخة بالدماء
these people alone were never conquered by the Spanish.
لم تعاني أبداً هذه القبيلة من الغزو الأسباني.
To this day, they remain ruled by a ritual priesthood
وإلى يومنا هذا، لا تزال تحت حكم كهنوتي
but the training for the priesthood is rather extraordinary.
ولكن ممارستهم للكهنوت تعتبر غير مألوفة.
The young acolytes are taken away from their families
حيث يتم أخذ مساعدي الكهنة الصغار بعيداً عن عائلاتهم
at the age of three and four,
في سن ثلاث و أربع سنوات
sequestered in a shadowy world of darkness
ويُحتجزون في عالم من الظلام
in stone huts at the base of glaciers for 18 years:
في أكواخ صخرية في قاعدة الأنهار الجليدية لمدة 18 عاماً.
two nine-year periods
على فترتين، مدة الفترة الواحدة تسع سنوات
deliberately chosen to mimic the nine months of gestation
تم اختيارهم عن عمد لتشبه أشهر الحمل التسعة
they spend in their natural mother's womb;
التي يقضونها في رحم أمهاتهم الطبيعي
now they are metaphorically in the womb of the great mother.
والآن هم يعتبرون في رحم الطبيعة الأم
And for this entire time,
وخلال كل هذا الوقت.
they are inculturated into the values of their society,
يتم غرس قيم المجتمع التابعين له
values that maintain the proposition that their prayers
وهي قيم تحتفظ بالحالة التي تكون فيها صلواتهم
and their prayers alone maintain the cosmic --
وصلواتهم فقط هي التي تحافظ على الكون --
or we might say the ecological -- balance.
أو ما يمكن أن نطلق عليه التوازن البيئي
And at the end of this amazing initiation,
وفي نهاية هذا الاستهلال العجيب
one day they're suddenly taken out
ويوم ما يتم أخذهم فجأة
and for the first time in their lives, at the age of 18,
ولأول مرة في حياتهم، في عمر 18 عاماً
they see a sunrise. And in that crystal moment of awareness
يرون شروق الشمس. وفي تلك اللحظة الجلية للوعي
of first light as the Sun begins to bathe the slopes
لأول ضوء عندما تبدأ الشمس في نشر ضوئها
of the stunningly beautiful landscape,
على الأفق الرائع المنظر
suddenly everything they have learned in the abstract
فجأة يصبح كل شيء قد تعلموه
is affirmed in stunning glory. And the priest steps back
مؤكداً في مجد آخاذ. ثم يتراجع الكاهن
and says, "You see? It's really as I've told you.
ويقول، "هل ترى؟ إنها فعلا كما أخبرتك.
It is that beautiful. It is yours to protect."
إنها جميلة فعلاً. وهي لك لتحميها.
They call themselves the "elder brothers"
وهم يسمون أنفسهم الأخوة الكبار
and they say we, who are the younger brothers,
ويقولون عنا نحن، أننا الأخوة الصغار
are the ones responsible for destroying the world.
المسئولين عن تدمير العالم
Now, this level of intuition becomes very important.
الآن، هذا المستوى من الحدس يصبح مهم جداً.
Whenever we think of indigenous people and landscape,
أينما نفكر في أناس محليين ومنظر عام
we either invoke Rousseau
فإننا نستدعي روسو
and the old canard of the "noble savage,"
والإشاعة الكاذبة القديمة للهمجي النبيل
which is an idea racist in its simplicity,
والتي هي فكرة عنصرية في بساطتها
or alternatively, we invoke Thoreau
أو بشكل بديل، نحن نستدعي ثورو
and say these people are closer to the Earth than we are.
ونقول أن هؤلاء الناس هم أقرب إلى الأرض منا نحن
Well, indigenous people are neither sentimental
حسناً، إن الناس المحليين ليسوا عاطفيين
nor weakened by nostalgia.
ولا يضعفهم الحنين
There's not a lot of room for either
لا يوجد مساحة كبيرة لأي من الاثنين
in the malarial swamps of the Asmat
في مستنقعات الملاريا في أسمت
or in the chilling winds of Tibet, but they have, nevertheless,
أو في الرياح الباردة بالتبت، ولكنهم، بالرغم من ذلك
through time and ritual, forged a traditional mystique of the Earth
من خلال الوقت والطقوس، كونوا غموضاً تقليدياً للأرض
that is based not on the idea of being self-consciously close to it,
وهذا لا يعتمد على فكرة كونك واعي ذاتياً
but on a far subtler intuition:
ولكن على حدس أبعد
the idea that the Earth itself can only exist
الفكرة في أن الأرض نفسها يمكن أن توجد فقط
because it is breathed into being by human consciousness.
لأنها تستمد الوجود من الوعي البشري
Now, what does that mean?
الآن، ماذا يعني ذلك؟
It means that a young kid from the Andes
يعني أن طفل صغير من الإنديز
who's raised to believe that that mountain is an Apu spirit
تمت تربيته ليعتقد أن الجبل روح "أبو"
that will direct his or her destiny
الذي سيوجه أو يوجهها إلى مصيره أو مصيرها
will be a profoundly different human being
سيكون إنسان مختلف تماماً
and have a different relationship to that resource
وسيكون له علاقة مختلفة بهذا المورد
or that place than a young kid from Montana
أو ذلك المكان عن طفل صغير من مونتانا
raised to believe that a mountain is a pile of rock
تمت تربيته ليؤمن أن الجبل هو حفنة من الصخور
ready to be mined.
جاهز ليتم حفره كمناجم
Whether it's the abode of a spirit or a pile of ore is irrelevant.
سواء إذا كان مأوى للروح أو كمية من الذهب الخام فهو أمر لا يهم
What's interesting is the metaphor that defines the relationship
الشيء المثير هنا هو المجاز الذي يحدد العلاقة
between the individual and the natural world.
بين الفرد والعالم الطبيعي
I was raised in the forests of British Columbia
لقد نشأت في غابات "بريتش كولومبيا"
to believe those forests existed to be cut.
لأؤمن بأن هذه الغابات قد وجدت ليتم قطعها
That made me a different human being
وهذا جعلني إنسان مختلف
than my friends amongst the Kwagiulth
عن أصدقائي بين قبيلة الكواكوتي
who believe that those forests were the abode of Huxwhukw
الذين يعتقدون أن تلك الغابات هي مأوى الهوكوك
and the Crooked Beak of Heaven
والقمة المعقوفة للجنة
and the cannibal spirits that dwelled at the north end of the world,
وأرواح آكلي لحوم البشر التي قطنت في النهاية الشمالية للعالم
spirits they would have to engage during their Hamatsa initiation.
أرواح يجب أن يتعاملوا معها أثناء استهلال "هاماتسا"
Now, if you begin to look at the idea
الآن، إذا بدأت تنظر إلى فكرة
that these cultures could create different realities,
أن هذه الثقافات يمكن أن تخلق حقائق مختلفة
you could begin to understand
يمكن أن تبدأ أن تفهم
some of their extraordinary discoveries. Take this plant here.
بعض اكتشافاتهم المذهلة. خذ هذا النبات هنا
It's a photograph I took in the Northwest Amazon just last April.
إنها صورة التقطتها في شمال غرب الأمازون في أبريل الماضي فقط
This is ayahuasca, which many of you have heard about,
هذه هي "أياهواسكا"، والتي سمع العديد منكم عنها
the most powerful psychoactive preparation
أقوى مستحضر تأثير نفسي
of the shaman's repertoire.
بحسب تصانيف "شامان"
What makes ayahuasca fascinating
وهو ما يجعل "أياهواسكا" مبهراً
is not the sheer pharmacological potential of this preparation,
ليس إمكانية العقار الكبيرة لهذا الإعداد
but the elaboration of it. It's made really of two different sources:
ولكن التفصيل فيه. إنه مصنوع من مصدرين مختلفين
on the one hand, this woody liana
ومن ناحية، يوجد هذا النبات المتسلق الخشبي
which has in it a series of beta-carbolines,
والذي يملك سلسلة من البيتا كاربولين
harmine, harmaline, mildly hallucinogenic --
هارمين، هارمولين، يؤدي إلى الهلوسة
to take the vine alone
وعند أخذ العرق بمفرده
is rather to have sort of blue hazy smoke
تحس بدخان أزرق ضبابي
drift across your consciousness --
يتحرك نحو إدراكك
but it's mixed with the leaves of a shrub in the coffee family
ولكنه مخلوط بأوراق شجيرة في عائلة القهوة
called Psychotria viridis.
تسمى "سيكوتريا فيريديس"
This plant had in it some very powerful tryptamines,
يحتوي هذا النبات على بعض "التريبتامين" القوي جداً
very close to brain serotonin, dimethyltryptamine,
قريب جداً من "سيروتونين" المخ، دايمثيلتريبتامين
5-methoxydimethyltryptamine.
"5-ميثوإكسيدايمثيلتريبتامين"
If you've ever seen the Yanomami
إذا سبق لكم ورأيتم اليانومامي
blowing that snuff up their noses,
ينفخون هذا في أنوفهم
that substance they make from a different set of species
هذه المادة يصنعونها من مجموعة مختلفة من الكائنات
also contains methoxydimethyltryptamine.
وهي تحتوي أيضاً على "ميثوإكسيدايمثيلتريبتامين"
To have that powder blown up your nose
لكي يتم نفخ هذا المسحوق في أنفك
is rather like being shot out of a rifle barrel
تشعر كأنك تم إطلاقك من فوهة مدفع
lined with baroque paintings and landing on a sea of electricity. (Laughter)
مع ألوان مزخرفة وتهبط على بحر من الكهرباء. (ضحك)
It doesn't create the distortion of reality;
إنه لا يحرف الواقع
it creates the dissolution of reality.
لكن يدمره من الأساس.
In fact, I used to argue with my professor, Richard Evan Shultes --
في الحقيقة، اعتدت أن أناقش أستاذي، ريشارد إيفان شولتز --
who is a man who sparked the psychedelic era
من هو الرجل الذي أطلق شرارة عهد مخدرات الهلوسة
with his discovery of the magic mushrooms
باكتشافه عيش الغراب السحري
in Mexico in the 1930s --
في المكسيك في الثلاثينيات
I used to argue that you couldn't classify these tryptamines
واعتدت أن أناقش أنه لا يمكنك تصنيف هذه "التريبتامينات"
as hallucinogenic because by the time you're under the effects
كمواد هلوسة لأنه في الوقت الذي تكون فيه تحت تأثيره
there's no one home anymore to experience a hallucination. (Laughter)
لا يعد يوجد أحد بالمنزل لتجربة الهلوسة
But the thing about tryptamines is they cannot be taken orally
ولكن الشيء الغريب عن التريبتامين هو أنه لا يمكن أن يتم تعاطيه بالفم
because they're denatured by an enzyme
لأنه يتم تغيير طبيعته بواسطة إنزيم
found naturally in the human gut called monoamine oxidase.
موجود طبيعياً في أمعاء الإنسان يسمى "مونوأمين أوكسيداس"
They can only be taken orally if taken in conjunction
يمكن تعاطيه بالفم فقط إذا تم تعاطيه مع
with some other chemical that denatures the MAO.
بعض الكيماويات الأخرى التي تغير طبيعة "مونوأمين أوكسيداس"
Now, the fascinating things
الآن، الأشياء المذهلة
are that the beta-carbolines found within that liana
هي أن البيتا كاربولين الموجودة في هذا النبات المتسلق الخشبي
are MAO inhibitors of the precise sort necessary
هي مانعات "مونوأمين أوكسيداس" للنوع المحدد الضروري
to potentiate the tryptamine. So you ask yourself a question.
لتحريض "التربتامين". ولذلك تسأل نفسك سؤالا
How, in a flora of 80,000 species of vascular plants,
كيف لمملكة نباتية مكونة من 80000 نوع نبات
do these people find these two morphologically unrelated plants
أمكن لهؤلاء الناس العثور على نباتين غير مترابطين مورفولوجيا
that when combined in this way,
وعند جمعهم بهذه الطريقة
created a kind of biochemical version
تنتج نوعاً من الإصدار الكيميائي الحيوي
of the whole being greater than the sum of the parts?
للكائن ككل أكبر من مجموع الأجزاء
Well, we use that great euphemism, "trial and error,"
حسناً، نحن نسنتخدم هذه التورية، التجربة والخطأ،
which is exposed to be meaningless.
والتي يتضح أنها لا معنى لها
But you ask the Indians, and they say, "The plants talk to us."
ولكنك تسأل الهنود وهم يقولون "النباتات تتحدث إلينا."
Well, what does that mean?
حسناً، ما معنى هذا؟
This tribe, the Cofan, has 17 varieties of ayahuasca,
هذه القبيلة، "الكوفان"، لديها 17 نوع مختلف من "أياهواسكا"
all of which they distinguish a great distance in the forest,
وجميعا يميزونها من على مسافة بعيدة في الغابة
all of which are referable to our eye as one species.
والتي تراها أعيننا نحن كنوع واحد
And then you ask them how they establish their taxonomy
ثم تسألهم كيف قاموا بتصنيفهم
and they say, "I thought you knew something about plants.
وهم يقولون "لقد اعتقدت أنك تعرف عن النباتات
I mean, don't you know anything?" And I said, "No."
أقصد، ألا تعرف أي شيء؟" وكانت إجابتي "لا".
Well, it turns out you take each of the 17 varieties
حسناً، اتضح أنه تأخذ كل الـ 17 نوعاً
in the night of a full moon, and it sings to you in a different key.
في ليلة ذات قمر مكتمل، وهي تغني لك بصوت مختلف.
Now, that's not going to get you a Ph.D. at Harvard,
الآن، هذا لن يجعلك تحصل على درجة الدكتوراه في هارفارد
but it's a lot more interesting than counting stamens. (Laughter)
ولكنها أمراً أكثر تشويقاً من عد السداة.
Now --
الآن،
(Applause) --
(تصفيق)
the problem -- the problem is that even those of us
المشكلة - المشكلة هو أنه حتى نحن
sympathetic with the plight of indigenous people
المتعاطفين مع محنة السكان المحليين
view them as quaint and colorful
يرونهم عجيبين وذوي ألوان زاهية
but somehow reduced to the margins of history
ولكن تم تقليلهم بطريقة ما إلى هامش التاريخ
as the real world, meaning our world, moves on.
حيث أن العالم الحقيقي، ونعني عالمنا، يتحرك
Well, the truth is the 20th century, 300 years from now,
حسناً، الحقيقة هي القرن العشرين، 300 عام من الآن
is not going to be remembered for its wars
لن يتم تذكره بسبب حروبه
or its technological innovations,
أو اختراعاته التكنولوجية
but rather as the era in which we stood by
ولكن في العهد الذي نكون عليه
and either actively endorsed or passively accepted
وسواء كان تم تفويضه بنشاط أو قبوله بسلبية
the massive destruction of both biological and cultural diversity
التدمير الشامل لكلا من التعددية البيولوجية والثقافية
on the planet. Now, the problem isn't change.
على الكوكب. الآن، المشكلة ليست التغيير
All cultures through all time
إن كل الثقافات عبر التاريخ
have constantly been engaged in a dance
كانت مشتركة دائماً في رقصة
with new possibilities of life.
مع إمكانيات جديدة للحياة
And the problem is not technology itself.
والمشكلة ليست في التكنولوجيا ذاتها
The Sioux Indians did not stop being Sioux
إذ أن هنود "السيوكس" لم يكفوا على أن يكونوت "سيوكس"
when they gave up the bow and arrow
عندما تخلوا عن القوس والسهم
any more than an American stopped being an American
أكثر من أي أمريكي توقف عن أي يكون أمريكي
when he gave up the horse and buggy.
عندما تخلي عن الحصان والعربة
It's not change or technology
إنه ليس التغيير أو التكنولوجيا
that threatens the integrity of the ethnosphere. It is power,
الذي يهدد سلامة المحيط العرقي. أنها القوة
the crude face of domination.
الوجه الفظ للسيطرة
Wherever you look around the world,
وأينما تنظر حول العالم
you discover that these are not cultures destined to fade away;
تكتشف أن هذه ليست حضارات من قدرها أن تندثر
these are dynamic living peoples
هؤلاء إناس حيويين
being driven out of existence by identifiable forces
تم إخراجهم من الوجود بواسطة قوى معروفة
that are beyond their capacity to adapt to:
وهي أكبر من طاقتهم للتكيف معها.
whether it's the egregious deforestation
سواء أكان تدمير الغابات السافر
in the homeland of the Penan --
في وطن قبائل "البينان" --
a nomadic people from Southeast Asia, from Sarawak --
قوم رحالة من جنوب شرق آسيا، من قبائل " ساراواك" --
a people who lived free in the forest until a generation ago,
شعب عاش حراً في الغابة حتى جيل مضى
and now have all been reduced to servitude and prostitution
وتم الآن تقليلهم للعبودية والدعارة
on the banks of the rivers,
على ضفاف الأنهار
where you can see the river itself is soiled with the silt
حيث يمكنك رؤية النهر نفسه وهو ملئ بالطمي
that seems to be carrying half of Borneo away
والذي يبدو وأنه يحمل نصف "البورنيو" بعيداً
to the South China Sea,
إلى بحر جنوب الصين
where the Japanese freighters hang light in the horizon
حيث تجد الناقلات اليابانية منتظرة في الأفق
ready to fill their holds with raw logs ripped from the forest --
جاهزة لملء جنباتها بالأشجار الخام المقطوعة من الغابة.
or, in the case of the Yanomami,
أو في حالة اليانومامي
it's the disease entities that have come in,
إنه المرض.
in the wake of the discovery of gold.
في صحوة اكتشاف الذهب.
Or if we go into the mountains of Tibet,
أو إذا ذهبنا إلى جبال التبت،
where I'm doing a lot of research recently,
حيث أجري مؤخراً العديد من الأبحاث
you'll see it's a crude face of political domination.
سترى أنه الوجه الفظ للسيطرة السياسية.
You know, genocide, the physical extinction of a people
تعرفون، الإبادة الجماعية، الإبادة المادية للبشر
is universally condemned, but ethnocide,
شيء مشجوب عالمياً، ولكن التطهير العرقي
the destruction of people's way of life, is not only not condemned,
تدمير طريقة الناس في الحياة، ليست فقط غير مدانة
it's universally, in many quarters, celebrated
إنها وبصورة عالمية -- في أنحاء كثيرة -- يتم الإحتفال بها
as part of a development strategy.
كجزء من استراتيجية التنمية
And you cannot understand the pain of Tibet
ولا يمكنك فهم ألم التبت
until you move through it at the ground level.
حتى تعيش فيه على المستوى الفردي
I once travelled 6,000 miles from Chengdu in Western China
لقد سافرت مرة 6000 ميل من شينجدو في غرب الصين
overland through southeastern Tibet to Lhasa
عبر البر خلال جنوب شرق التبت إلى "لهاسا"
with a young colleague, and it was only when I got to Lhasa
مع زميل شاب، وقد كان فقط عندما وصلت إلى "لهاسا"
that I understood the face behind the statistics
حتى فهمت الوجه وراء الاحصائيات
you hear about:
التي تسمع عنها
6,000 sacred monuments torn apart to dust and ashes,
حيث تم تدمير 6000 أثر مقدس إلى تراب ورماد
1.2 million people killed by the cadres
تم قتل 1.2 مليون شخص بواسطة السلطات
during the Cultural Revolution.
خلال الثورة الثقافية
This young man's father had been ascribed to the Panchen Lama.
كما أن والد هذا الشاب وجهت إليه تهمة اتباع البانشين لاما
That meant he was instantly killed
وهذا يعني أنه تم قتله على الفور
at the time of the Chinese invasion.
في وقت الغزو الصيني
His uncle fled with His Holiness in the Diaspora
إذ فر عمه مع قداسته إلى الشتات
that took the people to Nepal.
الذي أخذ الناس إلى نيبال
His mother was incarcerated
تم سجن والدته بثمن --
for the crime of being wealthy.
بسبب جريمة أنها ثرية
He was smuggled into the jail at the age of two
تم تهريبه داخل السجن في عمر سنتين
to hide beneath her skirt tails
ليختبأ تحت ذيل تنورتها
because she couldn't bear to be without him.
لأنها لم تتحمل أن تكون بدونه
The sister who had done that brave deed
الأخت التي قامت بهذا العمل الشجاع
was put into an education camp.
تم وضعها في معسكر تعليم
One day she inadvertently stepped on an armband
وفي إحدى الأيام وطأت بقدمها بدون قصد على رباط ذراع
of Mao, and for that transgression,
خاص "بماو"، وبسبب هذا الاعتداء
she was given seven years of hard labor.
تم الحكم عليها بسبع سنوات أشغال شاقة
The pain of Tibet can be impossible to bear,
ألم التبت لا يمكن تحمله
but the redemptive spirit of the people is something to behold.
ولكن روح فداء الشعب شيء تتوقف أمامه
And in the end, then, it really comes down to a choice:
وفي النهاية، تأتي الأمور إلى اختيار
do we want to live in a monochromatic world of monotony
هل تريد العيش في عالم من الرتابة أحادي اللون
or do we want to embrace a polychromatic world of diversity?
أو هل تريد العيش في عالممن التعددية مختلف الألوان ؟
Margaret Mead, the great anthropologist, said, before she died,
"مارجريت ميد"، عالمة الأنثروبيولوجي العظيمة، قالت قبل أن تموت
that her greatest fear was that as we drifted towards
أن أكبر مخاوفها هو أننا اتجهنا نحو
this blandly amorphous generic world view
هذه النظرة العالمية العامة
not only would we see the entire range of the human imagination
لن نرى فقط النطاق الكامل للخيال البشري
reduced to a more narrow modality of thought,
وقد اختزل إلى فكر ضيق
but that we would wake from a dream one day
ولكننا قد نستيقظ من حلم في يوم ما
having forgotten there were even other possibilities.
وقد نسينا أنه يوجد حتى إمكانيات أخرى
And it's humbling to remember that our species has, perhaps,
وهو أمر مهين أن نتذكر أنه كان هناك كائنات
been around for [150,000] years.
ربما لفترة 150000 سنة
The Neolithic Revolution -- which gave us agriculture,
الثورة الحجرية -- التي منحتنا الزراعة
at which time we succumbed to the cult of the seed;
حيث إنصعنا إلى البذور
the poetry of the shaman was displaced
شعر الشامان قد تم استبداله
by the prose of the priesthood;
بواسطة نثر الكهنوت
we created hierarchy specialization surplus --
لقد خلقنا فائض تخصص هرمي --
is only 10,000 years ago.
هو 10000 عام مضت فقط
The modern industrial world as we know it
العالم الصناعي الحديث كما نعرفه
is barely 300 years old.
هو منذ 300 عام مضت فقط
Now, that shallow history doesn't suggest to me
الآن، التاريخ الضحل لا يظهر لي
that we have all the answers for all of the challenges
أنه لدينا كل الإجابات لكل التحديات
that will confront us in the ensuing millennia.
التي تواجهنا في الألفية
When these myriad cultures of the world
عندما تسأل هذه الثقافات التي لا حصر لها في العالم
are asked the meaning of being human,
عن معنى أن تكون إنسانا
they respond with 10,000 different voices.
فهم يردون بـ 10000 صوت مختلف
And it's within that song that we will all rediscover the possibility
وهي في هذه الأغنية التي سنعيد اكتشاف إمكانية
of being what we are: a fully conscious species,
أن نكون ما نكون عليه: مخلوقات واعية تماماً
fully aware of ensuring that all peoples and all gardens
مدركين تماماً التأكيد على أن كل الناس وكل الحدائق
find a way to flourish. And there are great moments of optimism.
تجد طريقة للإزهار. ويوجد لحظات عظيمة من التفاؤل.
This is a photograph I took at the northern tip of Baffin Island
هذه صورة التقطتها في الطرف الشمالي لجزيرة بافن
when I went narwhal hunting with some Inuit people,
عندما ذهبت للصيد مع بعض الإنويت
and this man, Olayuk, told me a marvelous story of his grandfather.
وهذا الرجل، "أولايا"، أخبرني قصة رائعة عن جده
The Canadian government has not always been kind
لم تكن الحكومة الكندية عطوفة دائماً
to the Inuit people, and during the 1950s,
على شعب "الإنويت"، وخلال الخمسينيات
to establish our sovereignty, we forced them into settlements.
ولترسيخ سيادتنا، أجبرناهم على العيش في مستوطنات
This old man's grandfather refused to go.
ورفض جد هذا الرجل أن يذهب
The family, fearful for his life, took away all of his weapons,
والعائلة، خوفاً على حياته، أخذت كل أسلحته
all of his tools.
كل أدواته
Now, you must understand that the Inuit did not fear the cold;
الآن، يجب أن تعرف أن "الإنويت" لم يخافوا البرد
they took advantage of it.
لقد استفادوا منه
The runners of their sleds were originally made of fish
فركائز زلاقاتهم كانت مصنوعة في الأساس من السمك
wrapped in caribou hide.
وملفوفة بجلد حيوان الرنة
So, this man's grandfather was not intimidated by the Arctic night
ولذلك، لم يكن جد هذا الرجل مرعوب بواسطة ليل القطب الشمالي
or the blizzard that was blowing.
أو العاصفة الثلجية التي كانت تهب
He simply slipped outside, pulled down his sealskin trousers
فقد انزلق ببساطة في الخارج، وأنزل بنطاله المصنوع من جلد الفقمة
and defecated into his hand. And as the feces began to freeze,
وتبرز في يديه. وعندما بدء البراز في التجمد
he shaped it into the form of a blade.
قام بتشكيله على شكل شفرة
He put a spray of saliva on the edge of the shit knife
ووضع لعابه على حافة سكين البراز
and as it finally froze solid, he butchered a dog with it.
وعندما تجمدت وأصبحت صلبة، قام بذبح كلب بها
He skinned the dog and improvised a harness,
وسلخ الكلب وارتجل سرج
took the ribcage of the dog and improvised a sled,
وأخذ القفص الصدري للكلب وارتجل زلاقة
harnessed up an adjacent dog,
وربط كلب في السرج
and disappeared over the ice floes, shit knife in belt.
واختفى فوق الجليد، وسكين البراز في حزامه
Talk about getting by with nothing. (Laughter)
تحدث عن التكيف بدون أي شيء&lt;ضحك&gt;
And this, in many ways --
وهذا، بطرق عديدة
(Applause) --
.
is a symbol of the resilience of the Inuit people
رمز لمرونة شعب الإنويت
and of all indigenous people around the world.
وكل الشعوب المحلية حول العالم
The Canadian government in April of 1999
أعادت الحكومة الكندية في أبريل 1999
gave back to total control of the Inuit
السيطرة الكاملة لشعب الإنويت
an area of land larger than California and Texas put together.
على منطقة من الأرض أكبر من كاليفورنيا وتكساس مجتمعتين
It's our new homeland. It's called Nunavut.
إنه وطننا الجديد. وهو يسمى نونافيت
It's an independent territory. They control all mineral resources.
وهو إقليم مستقل. هم يتحكمون في كل الموارد المعدنية.
An amazing example of how a nation-state
مثال رائع في كيف يمكن لدولة - أمة
can seek restitution with its people.
يمكن أن تصل إلى -- تسعى إلى إرجاع الشيء لأصله مع شعبها
And finally, in the end, I think it's pretty obvious
وأخيراً، في النهاية، أعتقد أنه جلي جداً
at least to all of all us who've traveled
على الأقل لجميعنا ممن سافروا
in these remote reaches of the planet,
إلى هذه المناطق البعيدة من الكوكب
to realize that they're not remote at all.
لكي يدركوا أنهم ليسوا بعيدين على الإطلاق
They're homelands of somebody.
إنهم في أوطان إناس ما
They represent branches of the human imagination
هم يقدمون أفرع من الخيال البشري
that go back to the dawn of time. And for all of us,
تعود إلى فجر التاريخ. ولكل منا
the dreams of these children, like the dreams of our own children,
أحلام هذه الأطفال، مثل أحلام أطفالنا
become part of the naked geography of hope.
تصبح جزء من الجغرافيا العارية للأمل
So, what we're trying to do at the National Geographic, finally,
ولذلك، ما نحاول أن نفعله في ناشيونال جيوغرافيك في النهاية
is, we believe that politicians will never accomplish anything.
هو أننا نؤمن بأن السياسيين لن ينجزوا أي شيء
We think that polemics --
نحن نعتقد أن المجادلين --
(Applause) --
&lt;تصفيق&gt;
we think that polemics are not persuasive,
نحن نعتقد أن المجادلين غير مقنعين
but we think that storytelling can change the world,
ولكننا نعتقد أن حكاية القصص يمكن أن تغير العالم
and so we are probably the best storytelling institution
ولذلك فإننا أفضل معهد لحكاية القصص في العالم
in the world. We get 35 million hits on our website every month.
تقريباً. نستقبل 35 مليون زيارة على موقعنا كل شهر.
156 nations carry our television channel.
156 دولة لديها قناتنا التلفزيونية
Our magazines are read by millions.
مجلاتنا يقرأها الملايين
And what we're doing is a series of journeys
وما نقوم به هو سلسلة من الرحلات
to the ethnosphere where we're going to take our audience
للمحيط العرقي حيث سنقوم باصطحاب مشاهدينا
to places of such cultural wonder
لأماكن ذات عجائب ثقافية
that they cannot help but come away dazzled
لا يمكن إلا أن يكونوا مبهورين
by what they have seen, and hopefully, therefore,
بما رأوه، ونأمل، نتيجة لذلك
embrace gradually, one by one,
أن يعتنقوا واحداً تلو الآخر
the central revelation of anthropology:
الإعلان الأساسي للأنثروبولوجيا:
that this world deserves to exist in a diverse way,
وهي أن هذا العالم يستحق أن يوجد بشكل متعدد
that we can find a way to live
أنه يمكننا أن نجد أسلوب للعيش
in a truly multicultural, pluralistic world
في عالم متعدد الثقافات بحق
where all of the wisdom of all peoples
حيث حكمة كل الناس
can contribute to our collective well-being.
يمكنها أن تسهم في رفاهيتنا الجماعية
Thank you very much.
شكراً جزيلاً
(Applause)
(تصفيق)